NYSUT Legislative Department Files. 6174/005
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Legislative Department Files
1884- 2005
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/005
15.5 cubic feet
15.5 linear ft.
Articles, reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
6477216
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
P. Leary, April 23, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 29, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
NYSUT's Legislative Department, a relatively small unit composed of just about a dozen members, was the engine behind the political powerhouse NYSUT had become by the 1980s. Reporting to the executive vice president, the department coordinated with the Legal Department and the Division of Research and Educational Services to develop an annual Legislative Program for the union, and then to push it relentlessly though the state legislature, from finding a sponsor for it in the Assembly or Senate, until it was signed by the governor. In addition to initiating legislation, the department tracked bills proposed independently by legislators, including proposals it considered detrimental to NYSUT's interests. All bills -- typically, some 15,000 per session -- would be reviewed. Of those 15,000, the approximately 3,000 that were determined to have an impact on education or health care were tracked on a daily basis by the department's electronic monitoring system. Receiving especially careful scrutiny was the annual budget proposed by the governor, for its impact on state aid to public education, including higher education provided by the State University of New York (SUNY) and its community colleges, and the City University of New York (CUNY). NYSUT's affiliate, United University Professions (UUP), regularly coordinated lobbying efforts with the department on behalf of higher education funding. The Legislative Department's overall lobbying operation was carried out not only by its professional staff in one-on-one contacts with individual legislators, but by a large group of volunteers, including retirees, who comprised its Committee of 100. Appointed by local presidents throughout the state, these teachers, school bus drivers, cafeteria ladies (aka School-Related Personnel), community college local presidents, and nurses (though NYSUT's affiliate, Federation of Nurses and Health Professionals), converged on Albany at least once a year, like birds returning in spring, to visit their local legislators on targeted, high-priority pending legislation.
In addition to state legislation, federal initiatives were also on the radar of the Legislative Department. The department knew what laws were in the congressional pipeline and who was behind them, and let them know of NYSUT's interest. The Legislative Department's purview included recommending endorsements to the NYSUT Board of Directors -- for president, Congress, and statewide down to the Assembly district level -- and then working with NYSUT's political action committee, VOTE/COPE (Committee on Political Education), to elect (or reelect) those candidates through a massive effort including phonebanks to members, specially printed campaign literature, and direct financial contributions.
Areas of interest to NYSUT included not only specific funding formulas for school aid, but state taxation broadly, because it knew that any reduction in revenues could ultimately be taken out of education funding. Legislation could be as narrow as giving state retirement service credit for Korean War veterans to issues affecting all public employees, such as the permanent COLA (cost of living adjustment) for retirees and the Triborough amendment to the Taylor Law, governing contract agreements. Thus the Legislative Department maintained contacts with a wide array of organizations and was itself a resource to elected and appointed officials. Led in the 1980s and 1990s by director of legislation Ray Skuse, a former Republican member of Assembly, the department worked equally well with Republicans and Democrats. The successive NYSUT executive vice presidents to whom the department reported, Dan Sanders, Herb Magidson, and Alan Lubin, all rose from the ranks of NYSUT's affiliate in New York City, the United Federation of Teachers (UFT), the political proving ground headed by Albert Shanker.
Scope and Contents
1973-2005. Majority of materials cover 1990s, some 1980s. Contents include issues briefing materials for lobbying days by Committee of 100, members of NYSUT, including retirees, who volunteered to lobby legislators in Albany; voter registration and issues flyers by VOTE/COPE (Committee on Political Education), the political action committee of NYSUT; recommendations for candidate endorsements and related background materials (research on voting records, summaries of key legislation); resolutions for consideration at the NYSUT Representative Assembly; correspondence with elected officials; draft legislation initiated by NYSUT; legislative memoranda of support or opposition to specific bills; annual NYSUT legislative programs (comprehensive package of bills of interest to K-12 public education, higher education, and health professionals); analyses of proposed executive (governor's) budgets; annual reports on legislative sessions, including bills opposed by NYSUT and not passed, bills passed by one chamber, vetoed, or signed into law
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Teachers' union, New York (State); Magidson, Herb; Sanders, Dan; Shanker, Albert; Skuse, Ray; New York State United Teachers. Archives; New York State United Teachers, Legislative Department; New York State United Teachers, Political Action Committee; New York State United Teachers, Committee of 100
6477216
- RA 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Convention Call; NYSUT Constitution, May 1993; nomination form for SRP Employee of the Year; list of committees; action items; memos re VOTE/COPE reception, Local Presidents' Conference; invitations to elected officials; draft working script for "Leaders of the PAC"
- RA 1997 (folder 2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Final Legislative Report, 1996; proposed constitutional amendments and resolutions; VOTE/COPE list of award-winning locals for 1996; Legislative Update (special RA report), "A Constitutional Convention in NYS?"; form letters to elected representatives re educational issues, available on NYSUT web site; minutes of NYSUT Board of Directors meeting of February 28-March 1, 1997; agenda for May 1 meeting; briefing bulletins for Board of Directors
- Community College Luncheon, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  December 12, 1997. Letters of invitation to community college presidents; list of attendees from NYSUT and community colleges; testimony of Alan Lubin, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Assembly Standing Committee on Higher Education, "Community Colleges: Strengthening Their Financial Support Structure," October 30; SUNY press release, "Chancellor to Submit 1998-99 State University Budget: Further Investment in Community Colleges is Central Focus of the Preposed $1.596 Billion Spending Plan"
- UFT/NYSUT Lobby Day, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  June 4, 1997. Memos re pension and retirement lobby day in Albany; luncheon menu and facilitative correspondence
- Todd French (Constitutional Convention), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Prospectus for final report re issues surrounding 1967 constitutional convention and 1997 constitutional convention referendum; correspondence with researcher
- Legislative Reception, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  February 3, 1997. Invitations; list of key legislative staff; menus, invoices, and other facilitative correspondence with caterers and others
- UUP Dinner Meeting- Fort Orange Club, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  December 16, 1996. Invitation on behalf of NYSUT and United University Professions to holiday dinner meeting, noting agenda to discuss future of SUNY colleges of technology; memo re Strategic Alliance of ag and tech colleges
- 1996 Campaign (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Clinton campaign bumper stickers; primary election results by congressional districts, Assembly districts and senate districts; memo re campaign printing and mailing operation; memo to AFT political director, requesting campaign supplies; list of NYSUT delegates and alternates to 1996 Democratic National Convention; memos re phone bank assistance for Rep. Hinchey and other priority candidates
- Committee of 100-Vouchers, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Lists of members of Committee of 100; expense reimbursement vouchers
- Committee of 100, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  3/25-26/1996. Notice to members re lobby day; memo re need for follow-up with legislator re school funding formula, including notes of visit; facilitative correspondence with hotel; expense invoices
- Committee of 100, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  5/13-14/1996. Evaluation forms summarizing positions of legislators visited during lobby day; text of legislation in Assembly re school funding, January 24, 1995; list of 1996 participants in lobby day; facilitative correspondence
- Committee of 100, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence and tentative agenda for March 25-26, 1996, lobby day; lists of members of Committee of 100; list of United University Professions executive board; list of NYSUT School-Related Personnel Advisory Committee members
- Community College Luncheon, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  October 7, 1996. List of invitees to NYSUT annual community college luncheon; letters of invitation
- PEC Conference, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Sept. 29-Oct. 3, 1996. Tentative agenda and related information re Public Employee Conference annual convention
- NYS AFL-CIO Meeting Concord Hotel, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  9/8-12/1996. Convention call for 28th constitutional convention, including tentative program; description of workshops
- UFT Retiree Meeting Jeanne DiLorenzo, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  March 19, 1996. Letter from UFT Retired Teachers chapter leader DiLorenzo requesting that NYSUT officer Ray Skuse speak at meeting re legislative process in Albany, August 2, 1995
- ED 12 Retirees, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  April 24, 1996. Note re retiree lobby day; catering evaluation form; list of members attending
- Committee of 100-Bill Schultz, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Briefing booklet re education issues for Committee of 100 lobby day, March 25-26, 1996; list of members of education and finance committees; tip sheet on effective lobbying
- New Board Members Orientation, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  June 11, 1996. Agenda and notice to Administrative Committee
- NYS AFL-CIO Legislative Conference, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Agenda and cover letter re theme, "America Needs a Raise"; list of NYSUT legislative department staff attending
- National Conference of State Legislatures, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  St. Louis, MO July 27-31, 1996. Meeting schedule and related information
- Pension Security in a Changing Environment, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  June 11-12, 1996. Conference brochure, "Pension Security in a Changing Environment," cosponsored by NYS and Local Retirement Systems and Government Law Center of Albany Law School; correspondence re NYSUT attendees
- Departmental Meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Memo re weekly meeting schedule; catering evaluation forms
- Empire State Report Pension Conference, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  NYC March 20-21, 1996. Empire State Report invitational brochure, "Public Pension Investment Policy Conference"; registration forms for NYSUT legislative staff
- AFT-AFL Meetings, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  February 1996. Facilitative materials
- Public Employee Conference Legislative Breakfast, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  February 6, 1996. Notice re NYS Public Employee Conference 19th Annual Legislative Breakfast; related correspondence
- NYSUT Legislative Reception, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  January 29, 1996. Letters of invitation; menu, invoices, and other facilitative correspondence
- Higher Education Lobby Day, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  March 11-12, 1996. List of attendees; facilitative correspondence
- Representative Assembly, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Convention call and tentative program; tentative program for pre-RA Local Presidents' Conference; NYSUT constitution, May 1993; proposed guest list of elected officials; form letters on educational issues to be sent to elected representatives, prepared for delegates visiting Political Action Center at conference; facilitative correspondence
- RA Material, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Report of the Resolutions Committees; special orders of business re elementary school standards, phase-out of Regents competency tests; Summary of PAC Activities (revised), December 1995-February 26, 1996; report of actions taken on constitutional amendments and resolutions; description of political action workshops; agenda for ED 12 Retiree Council Political Action Committee Training Day; invitation to VOTE/COPE reception for award-winning locals; awards program, listing locals; facilitative correspondence
- Committee of 100-Issues, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  May 11-12, 1998. Briefing book re legislative and budget proposals affecting public education
- Committee of 100, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  March 9-10, 1998. Agenda for lobbying day; issues briefing book; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees
- Committee of 100, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  May 19-20, 1997. Agenda for lobbying day; issues briefing book; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators
- Committee of 100, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  May 13-14, 1996. Agenda for lobbying day; issues briefing book; booklet, "New York State Tax Cuts: Promise or Peril?"; print ads/flyers re education and tax issues; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators
- Committee of 100, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  March 25-26, 1996. Agenda for lobbying day; issues briefing book; print ads/flyers re education and tax issues; tip sheet on effective lobbying; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; Legislative Update by NYSUT Legislative Department; list of elected official who have endorsed "Lessons for Life"
- Committee of 100, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  May 15-16, 1995. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; briefing papers re multi-year tax-cut proposals and other education issues; print ads/flyers re negative impact of tax cuts; NYSUT press release, "25 Percent of Teachers in NYSUT Survey Report Guns in Schools"; NYSUT Legislative Memorandum opposing multi-year tax cut
- Committee of 100, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  March 6-7, 1995. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; talking points on state aid to education; NYSUT press release, "NYSUT Committee of 100 to Press Case for More School Aid"; briefing paper, "Truth and Consequences-What the Executive Budget Doesn't Tell You about CUNY and SUNY!"; Testimony of Alan Lubin, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee on the 1995-96 Executive Budget, February 14, 1995
- Committee of 100, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  May 9-10, 1994. Agenda for lobbying day; issues briefing book; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of labor, civil service, and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators
- Committee of 100, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  March 21-22, 1994. Issues briefing book, "Seeking Support for Public Education, 1994-95"; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; list of sponsors of bill to further reduce corporate taxes; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; NYSUT Special Report, "School Decay: A Prescription for Recovery"; flyer by New York State School Boards Association calling for changes in 3020-a disciplinary process
- Committee of 100, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  May 17-18, 1993. Agenda for lobbying day; briefing book on pension, retirement and labor issues; background sheet re COLA: pension supplementation; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of labor, civil service, and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators
- Committee of 100, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  February 22-23, 1993. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; print ads/flyers re flawed tax system; report by American Economic Group, Inc., for NYSUT, "New York's 16 Billion Dollar Dilemma: Consequences of our state's well-intentioned tax cuts-and a plan to solve our revenue crisis"; Testimony of Herb Magidson, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Joint Committee of the NYS Senate Finance and Assembly Ways and Means Committees, January 26, 1993; Testimony on State Operations Budget, presented to Senate Finance Committee, Assembly Ways and Means Committee, by John M. Reilly, president, United University Professions, February 2, 1993; Statement by Dr. Irwin H. Polishook, president, Professional Staff Congress/CUNY, to the Assembly Ways and Means Committee and the Senate Finance Committee on the Executive Budget, 1993-94, for the City University of New York, February 2, 1993; NYSUT summary, Executive Budget Recommendations, 1993-94, SUNY and CUNY Colleges
- Committee of 100, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  May 18-19, 1992. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education, civil service, and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; briefing books, Pension and Retirement Issues, Higher Education Issues
- Committee of 100, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  February 24-25, 1992. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; NYSUT press release, "Statewide Survey: Increase Support for Public Education"; Fact Finders, Inc., survey results, "NYSUT Tracking of Public Attitudes Toward Education," February 20, 1992; Testimony of Herb Magidson, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee on the 1992-93 Executive Budget, February 4, 1992; letter from Magidson to state legislators re survey showing public support for increased public education funding, February 24; Testimony presented by John M. Reilly, president, United University Professions, before the Joint Hearing of the NYS Senate Finance Committee and the NYS Assembly Ways and Means Committee, January 28, 1992; Testimony presented by Dr. Irwin H. Polishook, president, Professional Staff Congress/CUNY, before the Joint Hearing of the NYS Assembly Ways and Means Committee and NYS Senate Finance Committee, January 28, 1992
- Committee of 100, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  May 13-14, 1991. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education, civil service, and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; NYSUT press release; NYSUT report, "The Impact of Executive Proposals on State Aid to Public Education 1991-92"; "1991 NYSUT Legislative Program for Pension Equity"; NYSUT Legislative Memorandum in support of early retirement incentive; print ads/flyers re state budget
- Committee of 100, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  February 25-26, 1991. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of new legislators; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; briefing book, "SUNY, CUNY, and the Community Colleges State Aid 1991-92"; print ads/flyers; letter to legislators from Tom Hobart and Herb Magidson opposing cuts in education budget; editorial from Daily Gazette (Schenectady), "Cuomo's Regressive Record," February 19; Testimony of Herb Magidson, executive vice president, NYSUT, to the Senate Finance Committee and Assembly Ways and Means Committee on the 1991-92 Executive Budget, February 11, 1991; highlights of the governor's state aid proposal
- Higher Education Lobby Day (folder 1), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  March 3-4, 1997. Agenda for lobbying day; list of members of Senate and Assembly; list of members of education and finance committees; reporting sheet for lobbying meetings with individual legislators; tip sheet on effective lobbying; briefing materials for legislators; related testimony by NYSUT, UUP, and PSC/CUNY officers
- Higher Education Lobby Day (folder 2), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  March 3-4, 1997. Room lists and other facilitative correspondence
- Higher Education Lobby Day, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)